[Music]
let's talk about car training today and
the primary question I want to answer is
how heavy do you lift if you want to
maximize power in other words I'm trying
to develop my lower body power should I
do squats at ninety percent of my rope
my one right max 10 percent 50 percent
right and in other words should I do
something really light or something
heavy or combination somewhere the
middle both I don't really know today
we're gonna get into that answer but
first a word from our sponsor
yeah we don't have any sponsor assistant
actually I should let you talk your our
sponsors so all of you that subscribe
like share all that stuff really
appreciate it anyways back to your
answer well to understand the optimal
load for power we have to look at bomb
mechanics a little bit and if you know
me you know how much I hate math and
especially pot mechanics but this I
promise you if a dummy like me can
understand this you can too so we have
to take a look at what's called the
force velocity curve so we know that
power is equal to force multiplied by
velocity and we know that the
relationship between velocity and force
is inverse right so what you're seeing
here again is called the force velocity
curve and it's very simple
the heavier something is the slower you
can move it that doesn't take you know a
neurosurgeon to figure that out if I
said hey tomorrow in class right next
time we meet in class rather we're gonna
run a race and whoever wins the race
gets an automatic a in the class for the
whole year and you have to wear backpack
and that backpack can be filled with
five pounds 50 pounds or 500 pounds you
would all obviously pick the five pounds
so you know this relationship already
because you know the heavier something
gets the slower it moves it doesn't have
to be more complicated than that where
this intervenes with power though is the
derivation of this here's what I mean if
I can multiply no force in velocity
equal power I can generate what's called
a power curve okay so this is our answer
right how heavy do I lift if I want to
maximize power well that answer is going
to be wherever this graph this power
graph is the highest Gabe
what that's gonna tell you is is this
look at this part
the left or kind of right depending on
how you're looking part of the curve
well doing something that's really
really heavy and really forceful isn't
necessarily going to be the most
powerful because it's gonna be too heavy
and it's gonna make you move slow
imagine doing a one rep max deadlift
yeah you're gonna move a lot of force
and produce a lot of force in the ground
but a bowl won't be a lot of power
because it's too slow look at the other
end of the spectrum though okay imagine
doing a deadlift with three pounds okay
well that's not gonna be very powerful
either because although you'll move
really fast there's not enough mass I'm
just looking from the equation
perspective you got two things that
you're multiplying to get a third thing
you want both of these things to be as
high as possible but you know that these
two things are actually inversely
related so when one goes up the other
goes down so what that tells you is well
at some point there's gonna be enough of
both to give me the best possible number
on the other side of the equation maybe
Ryan can come up with some fancy
graphics for that that I just did with
my fingers if not man don't worry about
it it's not that complicated
we're like what go back watch the video
again you can rewind that's why I make
these videos why don't do all these
lectures are you stupid textbooks in
class to be honest with you
so you can learn at your own pace
biomechanics nerds flying through this
maybe skip the old video be with a
struggle like me watch a couple times
alright watch it a faster speed anyways
coming back near an idea okay so this
power curve says at some point there'll
be enough mass and enough velocity that
power will be highest but it won't be at
one end or the other end of this force
philosophy spectrum so if you're looking
ahead a little bit you want to answer
that question okay well how heavy do I
train if I want to maximize power well
according to the mathematics that's
gonna be about 30% so you should do that
deadlift at about 30% of your max or
that benchpress at 30% of the squat or
whatever okay and that's based on a
whole bunch of things that I don't
really want to get into some old science
with froth isolated frog cells and some
cool things like that if you were to
take any certification test especially
the NSCA CSCS and
asking you about the number or the
intensity which peak powers as optimized
the answer will be 30% okay and it's
based on all this but in real life
that's not true in fact the literature
shows us not true and it doesn't make
sense cognitive but again if you take
those exams right 30% get your answer
correct get your certification and move
on it's not entirely wrong either it's
just too over simplistic which I guess
is a bit of a redundant right there I
could've just said simplistic over
simplistic anyways here's what I mean
okay we know that under a couple of
different situations this force velocity
curve changes so if you get stronger not
only does your max force go up but the
curve shifts as well so people that
produce say we'll just use an example of
what does actually the exercise doesn't
matter but as you get stronger instead
of producing your peak power at thirty
percent of your one hour max you now
actually produce it at forty or fifty
percent and again look at the litter at
the literature this is what's gonna show
you stronger individuals don't have peak
power at 30 percent
it's more like 40 50 60 percent okay
another situation the type of exercise
matters so if you compare say a normal
benchpress to what's called that
benchpress throw so there are cool
machines you can use or I remember in
high school you see this manually when
we would just literally throw the
barbell catch with our own hands okay
the machines do that for you you can
throw it it catches it it lowers it back
down that's probably bits a for the
price to do but we didn't have a lot of
resources back then a point being a
dynamic movement versus a an isolated
movement that stops acceleration now if
you go back and watch one of the
five-minute videos I have on different
types of acceleration resistance versus
assistance acceleration you'll notice I
talk about that whole acceleration to
the end range emotional that really
comes to fruition here finishing the
exercise not slowing down like you would
in a bench press but going through the
end of the range of motion really
changes the power dynamic all right so
the benchpress actually the literature
does suggest that even for people that
are
be strong they're gonna peak peak power
is gonna occur at about 30% of your one
right max but if you were to throw that
implement that's just the curve to the
right again and maybe now that's at 40
or 50 percent okay so again the point
I'm getting at is now that you
understand the different weak bench
press some entrants throw but stable
movements versus dynamic movements peak
power is gonna always happen further
down the intensity spectrum for the more
dynamic movement other examples bigger
muscle groups more complicated muscle
groups also will shift it to the right
so again 30 percent for bench is not
terrible but that's probably not gonna
get you peak power in your squat those
more complicated bigger muscle group
movements happens at more like 40 50 60
% so we shift that thing that's right
notice a theme here the bigger the
muscle groups the stronger you are the
more acceleration the more dynamic the
movement all of those things shift the
curve to the right meaning that you need
to lift a little bit heavier load to
optimize your power well that goes even
further when we extend something more
like a like a squat to something like a
clean a jerk or a snatch instead of peak
power happening at 50 or so percent that
actually happens it closer to 80 90 100
percent depending on the individual and
this is one of the reasons why we talk
about this all the time but as a general
statement people that are Olympic
weightlifters or weight lifters are
going to be the most powerful athletes
or at least Express the most power in
their lifts than anyone else that's
because they spend most of their time
training in a method that optimizes or
maximizes I should say power output so
it's very very helpful for that to wrap
all that up and conclude here there are
sort of three scenarios in which you
shift the power curve or allow you to
lift a heavier load and produce a more
force number one those that are stronger
number two more dynamic movements and
number three bigger muscle groups all
right so any of those situations result
in you needing to do more weight okay so
what I want to do now though is actually
talk more specifically about programming
for power so
to give you this famous slide now I use
this in all of my stuff if you want to
watch in my hypertrophy fat loss
conditioning or speed videos you're
gonna see the same schematic for the
slide I like to talk about the concepts
and then I'll give you some methods the
reason I do this approach is if you hit
the concepts I promise you you're gonna
get improvements in power the method you
choose to do that doesn't matter as much
because there's infinite methods but
only a few concepts so power typically
you're gonna use complex movements I
don't see a lot of benefit in doing like
isolated single joint stuff for power
it's typically multi-joint more
complicated movements and even multi
movement patterns is great so combining
SADS doe with frontal or things like
that are a benefit so i'm run between 3
and 20 issues that's it can be even
higher if you're fairly well trained but
the key is something like 1 to 5 reps
per set ok so you can't get powerful by
not moving powerfully if you do more
than 4 or 5 reps in a row you start to
slow down you start to compromise power
and there's not a hard and fast rule on
5 but it's a pretty decent one typically
what we like to say is like hey 2 3 4 5
reps something that neighborhoods pretty
good for power you want to do more of it
well then do more sets all right so do 2
or 3 reps take a break 2 or 3 reps take
a break and do that a bunch of times
rather than 5 6 7 8 9 10 reps in a row
those last five six seven eight nine
reps are going to be slow pure and
simple
which is not aiding in power development
something else right the load that you
need to do in terms of the amount that
you need to lift probably somewhere
between like 30 and 75 percent of your 1
rep max but as we just talked about it
sort of depends I think it's fair to say
though a couple of things the literature
my experience and most of the coaches
that I think are good at this are gonna
recommend a couple of things number one
train across the full spectrum there are
benefits of getting faster there are
benefits to getting stronger no doubt so
you should do some really heavy stuff
you should do some really light and fast
stuff you should do some stuff at 30 40
60 70 80 train across stuff
full power spectrum it's gonna get you
the most bang for your buck but probably
spend most of your time in that 60 70 80
90 percent range 90 even really is
starting to push it for most people
probably more like 60 70 80 % it's we're
gonna get most of your power development
maximize your speed and with all your
repetitions of course good technique and
good quality movement all that but you
gotta go fast and then of course with
that you want to maximize your rest
between set the textbook definition
answer would be 2 to 5 minutes per set
any Olympic weightlifter a power lifters
gonna maximize that go 5 10 minutes
between set which this is one of the
reasons why they're in the gym for 3
hours and they did 15 total reps right
but you need to be able to do that
because the quality of the movement has
to be there you're not going to improve
your maximum power output by training at
80 percent and if you're not wrestling
enough in between sets and your power
production goes down that's no longer
helpful so really a ton of rest
the typical qaul will say is hey if
you're doing a speed or a power day and
that's really all you're doing today you
probably will leave the gym going I
didn't do anything today you won't have
a great sweat going you won't get a burn
your lungs are gonna be blown out you
might leave going oh man like I didn't
do anything
in fact we're on a bit of a tangent here
but this is one of reasons why I think
Sweden power training doesn't land very
well for general public people because
they want to go to the gym they pay the
money because they want to feel that
that empty in the gas tank and you don't
get that with speed or power training so
a lot of commercial gyms and I'll say
popular companies in this space will do
power training but they'll just add a
ton of reps right it's not actually
power training of course not right
you're doing endurance training you're
just using a typical power of movement
like a kettlebell swing or a jump and
you're making a conditioning drill but
that's not improving power don't be
fooled there unless you're incredibly
untrained then everything works for a
little bit right but that's not really
what we're talking about here we're
talking about optimal situations okay
and because the force velocity curve is
or it is that typically means your
movements should be at about 50 to 90
percent of max velocity you don't really
need to go higher than 90 percent of max
velocity because that means
mass is gonna have to fall off too much
and the same thing on the other end of
the spectrum with velocity it can't be
love much slower than 50% now I would
encourage you all to generate your own
force velocity curve if you've got a gym
aware or a 1000 unit or something like
that or any type of accelerometer you
can put on your barbell but those are
the basic concepts it doesn't matter
much oh it does matter but this is gonna
get you there right just just so we can
have some fun let's go over a few
different methods speeds want squats are
great medicine ball tosses throws hop
skip jump all those things are fantastic
for the upper body I love clapping
push-ups if you can or put some medicine
ball throws all great complex training
is another type of training which will
I'll get into separately but but that's
a fantastic way to Train the quick
version there is doing something very
heavy shaking it out for 5-10 seconds
and then doing something immediately
fast after that so it's a it's a very
good approach weight lifting movements
so by this I mean Olympic weight lifting
so snatch clean and jerk or variations
power clean hang snatch jerk split jerks
all the variations of those movements
are good in fact the jerk to me is the
best movement ever because it's pretty
simple it's fairly safe and you can
generate a ton of power snatch is
generally more powerful but complication
goes up and down it's a little bit
tricky to pull off and as I mentioned
jumps sprints plyometrics as long as
they're short and there's no fatigue
being induced these will all land you
pretty well in power ok another thing I
wants to talk about a separate video is
called cluster sets or you can google
this but there's actually a significant
amount of research in the last 10 years
on cluster sets ok this is imagine
you're doing 3 sets of 10 or rather 10
sets of 3 sorry instead of doing 1 2 3
reps taking a break you do one take a
little break to do take a little break 3
take a little break then take your
normal break you're effectively
improving the quality of each repetition
because you're giving yourself a little
bit more rest in between each rep would
keep you
more fresh optimizes power so we'll talk
more later in other videos about complex
and cluster training specifically but
for now I hope you learned a little bit
about pirate trainings don't screw it up
next time you go to train by doing
something too light or too heavy because
they would be shameful for you to all be
small pathetic and not powerful I'll
we'll see most of you some of you in
class in a few days are tomorrow or
whatever happens to land let's
appreciate it and let's get powerful
[Music]